[{"question":"Gram-negative cells stain pink because","a":"(d) they are receptive to antibiotics.","b":"(b) their peptidoglycan layer is thin.","c":"(c) their peptidoglycan layer is thick.","d":"(a) they have specialised lipids in their cell walls.","hint":"Their peptidoglycan layer is thin and does  not retain crystal violet stain like Ciram- positive bacteria do","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following regarding protists, in general, is false?","a":"(a) Protists are always parasitic","b":"(b) Protists are single-celled.","c":"(c) Protists are heterotrophic.","d":"(d) All of the above","hint":"Protists do not have a unifying characteristic other than being eukaryotic; they do not fit into the kingdoms of Plantae, Animalia and Fungi","correct":"d"},{"question":"An organism having cytoplasm, DNA and RNA  that would kill most other bacteria. This indicates   no cell wall is:","a":"(a) Cyanobacterium","b":"(b) Mycoplasma","c":"(c) Bacterium","d":"(d) Virus","hint":"Mycoplasma lacks cell wall but show  multiplication like bacteria, so that they are  termed as cell wall less bacteria.","correct":"b"},{"question":"Most of the antibiotics have no effect on viruses because:","a":"(a) they kill all bacteria which form host of virus.","b":"(b) viruses are too small in size for antibiotics to act on them.","c":"(c) viruses have no metabolism of their own.","d":"(d) viruses produce a thick covering and","hint":"Antibiotics are chemical substance that is produced by an organism which kills another organism. Antibiotics destroy an organism by inhibiting its metabolic process. As viruses have no metabolisen of their own, antibiotics have no effect on them","correct":"c"},{"question":"During the evolution of eukaryotes from  prokaryotes, which of the following did not  occur?","a":"(a) Infolding of the flexible cell membrane.","b":"(b) Loss of the cell wall.","c":"(c) A switch from aerobic to anaerobic metabolism.","d":"(d) Endosymbiosis of once free-living  prokaryotes","hint":"The environment was becoming oxygen-  rich. There was not a switch from acrobic  to anaerobic metabolism but vice versa.","correct":"c"},{"question":"A tooth scraping yields large numbers of corkscrew shaped bacteria. These bacteria are  referred to as:","a":"(a) Bacilli","b":"(b) Cocci","c":"(c) Spirilli","d":"(d) Helici","hint":"Spirilli are corkscrew shaped.","correct":"c"},{"question":"The bacterium Bacillus thuringiensis can withstand heating, dryness, and toxic chemicals  that it is probably able to form","a":"(a) Pseudopodia","b":"(b) Endotoxins","c":"(c) Endospores","d":"(d) Pili","hint":"Endospores are able to survive a wide range  of conditions","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following facts differentiates the   from other viruses?","a":"(a) DNA is the genetic material","b":"(b) Obligate parasites","c":"(c) RNA is the genetic material","d":"(d) Nucleo-protein nature","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following does not contain  chlorophyll","a":"(a) Fungi","b":"(b) Algae","c":"(c) Bryophyta","d":"(d)  Pteridophyta","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Pseudomycelium is a characteristic feature of","a":"(a) Mushroom","b":"(b) Muscor","c":"(c) Bread mould","d":"(d) Yeast","hint":"Pseudomycelium is characteristic feature of yeast.","correct":"d"},{"question":"Antibiotics are mostly obtained from:","a":"(a) Bacteria","b":"(b) Viruses","c":"(c) Angiosperms","d":"(d) Fungi","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Bacteria were regarded to be plants because","a":"(a) some of them are green.","b":"(b) they are present everywhere.","c":"(c) some of them cannot move.","d":"(d) they have a rigid cell wall.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Locomotory structures are absent in","a":"(a) Sporozoans","b":"(b) Ciliates","c":"(c) Zooflagellates","d":"(d) Rhizopods","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"How many kingdoms contain eukaryotes in  five kingdom system of classification of R.H  Whittaker?","a":"(a) Four kingdoms","b":"(b) One kingdom","c":"(c) Two kingdoms","d":"(d) Three kingdoms","hint":"The kingdoms were named Monera, Protista, fungi, plantac and Animalia. Four kingdoms contain eukaryotes except kingdom Monera, which contains prokaryotes.","correct":"a"},{"question":"Litmus is obtained from:","a":"(a) Lichen","b":"(b) Algae","c":"(c) Fungi","d":"(d) protozoa ","hint":"Litmus used as acid-base indicator, is   Lasallia pastalana","correct":"a"},{"question":"Litmus is obtained from:","a":"(a) Lichen","b":"(b) Algae","c":"(c) Fungi","d":"(d) protozoa ","hint":"Litmus used as acid-base indicator, is   Lasallia pastalana","correct":"a"},{"question":"A bacteriophage is","a":"(a) a virus attacking a bacterium","b":"(b) a bacterium attacking a virus.","c":"(c) stage in the life-cycle of bacterium.","d":"(d) a virus attacking another virus.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Blackwater fever is caused by:","a":"(a) Plasmodium malariae","b":"(b) Povale","c":"(c) P.falciparum","d":"(d) P.vivax","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Contractile vacuoles of  Paramorcium are  analogous to","a":"(a) Sweat glands of mammals","b":"(b) Urinifersus tubules","c":"(c) Gastrovascular cavity of Hydra","d":"(d) Typhiosole of earthworm","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The symbiotic association of fungi and algae is    called:","a":"(a) Lichen","b":"(b) Mycorrhiza","c":"(c) Rhizome","d":"(d) Endomycorrhiza","hint":"The symbiotic association of fungi and algae  and m  is called lichen","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following combinations of characters is true for slime moulds?","a":"(a) Parasitic, plasmodium with true walls,  spores dispersed by air currents.","b":"(b) Saptophytic, plasmodium without walls, spores dispersed by water.","c":"(c) Parasitic, plasmodium without walls, spores dispersed by water.","d":"(d) Saprophytic, plasmodium without walls. spores dispersed by air currents.","hint":"Myxomycetes are commonly called true  slime moulds. These are saprophytic and their vegetative phase is represented by a free living, mass of protoplasm without walls and produce haploid spores, which are dispersed by air currents, rain and mites","correct":"d"},{"question":"Nutritionally bacteria are:","a":"(a) Autotrophic","b":"(b) Symbiotic","c":"(c) Parasitic","d":"(d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which bacteria would function best in hot   temperatures (45-60°C?","a":"(a) Psychrophiles","b":"(b) Thermophiles","c":"(c) Mesophiles","d":"(d) All would do equally well","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"If the generation time of a bacterium after that period.","a":"(a) 64x10","b":"(b) 32x 10","c":"(c) 6x10","d":"(d) 40×10","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Smallest virus is","a":"(a) Foot and Mouth virus","b":"(b) Alfalfa Mosaic virus","c":"(c) Pseudomonas","d":"(d) TMV","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Yeast is an important source of","a":"(a) Vitamin C","b":"(b) Vitamin B","c":"(c) Vitamin A","d":"(d) Vitamin D","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"In manufacturing of bread, it becomes porous  doc to release of CO, by the action of:","a":"(a) Virus","b":"(b) Yeast","c":"(c) Bacteria","d":"(d) Protozoans","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct for  both blue-green algae and bacteria?","a":"(a) Both show anaerobic respiration.","b":"(b) Both have chlorophyll pigment.","c":"(c) Both are devoid of true nucleus.","d":"(d) None of the above","hint":"Cyanobacterial cells (blue-green algal cells) are larger and more elaborate than bacteria. In both the organisms, the cell structure is typically prokaryotic type, one envelope organisation with peptidoglycan wall, naked DNA Blue-green algae have chlorophyll bacteria is devoid of chlorophyll","correct":"c"},{"question":"The phylogenetic system of classification was   put forth by","a":"(a) Carolus Linnaeus","b":"(b) George Bentham and Joseph Dalton Hooker","c":"(c) Theophrastus","d":"(d) Adolf Engler and Karl Prantl","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Plasmodium, the parasite, belongs to class:Plasmodium, the parasite, belongs to class:","a":"(a) Sarcodina","b":"(b) Ciliata","c":"(c) Sporozos","d":"(d) Dinophyceae","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In the five kingdom system of classification,  include blue-green algae, nitrogen fixing bacteria  and methanogenic arhaebacteria","a":"(a) Monera","b":"(b) Fungi","c":"(c) Plantac","d":"(d) Protista","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which one of the following pairs is not correct matched?","a":"(a) Anahana  - Cyanobacteria","b":"(b) Amoeba - protozoa ","c":"(c) Gonyaalax  - Dinoflagellates","d":"(d) Albugo  - Chrysophytes","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The cell wall of fungi is made up of:","a":"(a) Chitin","b":"(b) Cellulose","c":"(c) Pectin","d":"(d) Suberin","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The main difference between Gram positive and   Gram negative bacteria lies in the composition of:","a":"(a) Cilia","b":"(b) Cell wall","c":"(c) Nucleolus","d":"(d) Cytoplasm","hint":"In Gram-positive bacteria, cell wall is 200-300 A thick and have 85% macopeptides and 1-2% lipids while in Gram-negative bacteria cell wall is 100-200 A thick and 12% mucopeptides are have 10-12% and 80-90% lipids.","correct":"b"},{"question":"LPP-1 is a:","a":"(a) Bacterium","b":"(b) Fungus","c":"(c) Bacteriophage","d":"(d) Cyanophage","hint":"LPP-1 was the first cyanophage to be discovered by Safferman and Morris. It was so named because it can infect three different type of blue green algae which are Lyngbya, Phormidium and Plectonema","correct":"d"},{"question":"Natural system of classification differs from artificial  system in:","a":"(a) employing only one floral trait","b":"(b) taking only one vegetative trait","c":"C) bringing out similarities and dissimilarities","d":"(d) developing evolutionary trends","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The genetic material in viruses is/are:","a":"(a) Only RNA","b":"(b) Only DNA","c":"(c) RNA and DNA both","d":"(d) RNA or DNA one nucleic acid in a virus","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following fungi are edible?","a":"(a) Agaricus campestris","b":"(b) Morchella esculenta","c":"(c) Podaxon produxis","d":"(d) All of the above","hint":"Agaricus campestris is a common field mushroom, Morchella excalenta having apothecia type of edible ascocarp and Podazon prodazis is also edible.","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which protist reproduces both by binary fission and conjugation?","a":"(a) Amocha","b":"(b) Paramecium","c":"(c) Euglena","d":"(d) Monocystis","hint":"","correct":"b"}]